<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iudgement of a most reuerend and learned man from beyond the seas concerning a threefold order of bishops, with a declaration of certaine other waightie points, concerning the discipline and gouernement of the Church.</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120819</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856012</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856012</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 279:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iudgement of a most reuerend and learned man from beyond the seas concerning a threefold order of bishops, with a declaration of certaine other waightie points, concerning the discipline and gouernement of the Church.</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
                  <author>Fielde, John, d. 1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Théodore de Bèze.</note>
                  <note>Original title not traced.</note>
                  <note>Translated by John Fielde.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A] B-C.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The iudgement of a learned man.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Cropped at fore-edge and foot.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21525:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IVDGEMENT OF A MOST REVEREND AND LEARNED MAN FROM BEYOND THE SEAS, CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING A THREEFOLD ORDER OF BISHOPS, WITH A DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLARATION OF CERTAINE OTHER WAIGHTIE POINTS, CONCERNING THE DISCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLINE AND GOVERNEMENT OF THE CHVRCH.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21525:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21525:2"/>
            <head>THE IVDGMENT OF A MOST REVEREND AND LEARNED MAN FROM BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſeas, concerning a threefolde order of Biſhops: with a declaration of certaine other waightie pointes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſcipline and gouernement of the church.</head>
            <p>We muſt needes make three biſhops.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Of God.</item>
               <item>2 Of man.</item>
               <item>3 Of the deuil.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Biſhop ordained of God, or ſet vp by the law of God, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare nothing els but their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which by an other more ſpeciall name, are called Paſtoures, whome (ſaieth Luke) the holy Ghoſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <note place="margin">Etheto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopon poykanein ten eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian tou theou.</note> Biſhops to feede the Church of GOD. And either of theſe names of Paſtour or of Biſhop, is proper to them in the newe Teſtament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Apoſtle doeth diſtinguiſh them from Apoſtles, Prophets, and Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, which were callings to endure for a tyme, Epheſ. 4. 11. and from Deacons, 1. Tim. 3. and Phil. 1. 1. for otherwiſe they
<pb facs="tcp:21525:3"/> are euery where called Elders, &amp; Paule doth call his Apoſtleſhip a Deaconſhip. Rom. 11. 13. But they are called Biſhops in regard of the ſheepe committed vnto them, as though a man ſhould call them watchmen of ouerſeers.</p>
               <p>Theſe now were one alone, as where any church had but one Paſtor, or more if the Church had more then one. And the meeting of them together ioyntly with their Elders, whom Paule calleth gouernours, of the other commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> name <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eureuſes Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion.</note> called, was the Elderſhip. Their duetie was to attend on the worde and praier, both publikely and priuately, and in common to gouerne the Church, as appeareth by many places of Scripture.</p>
               <p>That the ſame were ſubiect to magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, though prophane, appeareth not onely by the example of Chriſt the high Prieſt, and of the Apoſtles, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the expreſſe wordes of Paul, 1. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth. 2. and Luke 12. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21525:3"/>
               <head>OF THE BISHOP THAT is of man.</head>
               <p>THe Biſhop that is of man, that is to ſay, brought into the Church by the alone wiſedome of man, beſides the expreſſe word of God, is a certain pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er giuen to one certaine Paſtour aboue his other fellowes, yet limited with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain orders or rules prouided againſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. They which did beare this office of biſhop, are called biſhops in regard of their fellow Elders and the whole cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, as watchmen ſet ouer the clergie.</p>
               <p>That this calling was not brought in by the word, it is manifeſt by that, that there is not to be found in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, ſo much as one ſyllable, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by there may be the leaſt ſurmiſe of any ſuch thing. For although we doubt not, but all thinges ought to be done order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the lordes houſe, and therfore that ſome one ſhould be preſident in euery aſſembly, whom Iohn in the Reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeemeth to call the Angell of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And Auſten calleth the modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Proeſtota,</hi> yet this moderator of actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:21525:4"/> of the Church, ſauyng this one thing, that he was the firſt in order in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; had no authority ouer his felows, neither did hee exerciſe any higher of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Therefore the author of the epiſtle to the Hebrewes, as Hierome noteth, doeth cal the whole company of the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <note place="margin">Egoume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous. Hebr. 13.</note> gouernours; not any one certayne man. Such a one was Peter many times in the very aſſembly of the Apoſtles, of a great authoritie ſurely amongſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who were all otherwiſe equall, and yet he himſelfe one of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Apoſtles, ſent by his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to Samaria with Iohn, Act. 8. 14. and in the aſſembly giuing an account of his miniſtery, to thoſe which were of the Circumciſion, Acts 11. 2. But if any ſuch biſhoplike authoritie of any one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt, as there was afterwardes, had bin then, ſurely the apoſtles would haue ſet down their names euen at that tyme, in their letters which they ſent from one to another, eſpecially ſeeing Paule in his epiſtle to the Philip. doth name biſhops in the plural number, and Deacons: or there ſhould haue bene at
<pb facs="tcp:21525:4"/> leaſt ſome peculiar mention made of them. Which, ſeeing it is not done, it appeareth that amongeſt theſe gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, there was none in degree aboue their companions and fellow biſhops: but as occaſion ſerued, the Churches were gouerned by a fellowlike &amp; equal authoritie, among the fellow-elders in their elderſhips, he onely going before the reſt, whoſe godlines and authoritie, the company did moſt allow of.</p>
               <p>Epiphanius againſt the Arrians, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the contrary opinion: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the biſhop ordained by man, as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by God, doth bring forth three reaſons to the contrary. Two as it were out of the word of God: the third out of the hiſtory of thoſe tymes. The firſt place is, 1. Tim. 5. 1. Rebuke not an El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <note place="margin">Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ron me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peplexen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> &amp;c. whereby he gathereth, that Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie had ſome authoritie ouer the Elders, that is, the Paſtors of the church of Epheſus. But (be it ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of ſo woorthy a man) hee ſhould haue marked, that here an elder is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, he that is ſuch by age, not he that is a Paſtor, which is declared by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb facs="tcp:21525:5"/> next following of yong men. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> reote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>An other place is out of the ſame Epiſtle, Receyue not an accuſation agaynſt an Elder, the firſt of Timothie 5. 19. Whereby he gathereth, that the Elders were ſubiect to the Biſhops and tribunall ſeate. But who will graunt hym that Timothie was Biſhop of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus. For the hiſtory will eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell that, which the fathers doe report as certayne. For no man can denie that Timothie was one that accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied Paule, and therefore no biſhop aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to any one certaine place, who was ſent one while to this place, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to that, for the eſtabliſhing of the Churches: and finally, that he was an Euangeliſt, and not a biſhop of any one certayne flocke. I haue deſired thee (ſaieth hee) to abide at Epheſus, whileſt I went into Macedonia. And why ſo? namely, to looke to the Church which hee had begunne to eſtabliſh, vntill he were called for agayne, which he doth in the other epiſtle. What? and did the Apoſtle robbe the Epheſians of their Biſhop, without asking their church at
<pb facs="tcp:21525:5"/> the leaſt? Surely, when he went laſt to Ieruſalem, neuer mindyng to returne to Epheſus, eyther he would haue reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Timothie vnto them, or the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians would haue required him agayne of the Apoſtle, when hee put them in minde of ſo great danger at hand: or if another were to be put into his roume, hee would haue made expreſſe menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that his diuine Sermon. But he is ſayd to haue ſent for the Elders onely, and to haue warned them of the duetie belongyng to them all. Yet it need not ſeeme ſtraunge to any, that the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Timothie, a man indued with ſo many and ſo great giftes remainyng at Epheſus, did gouerne all thinges by his direction, as one in degree aboue the Elders, and by the Apoſtles authoritie appointed there for a tyme.</p>
               <p>But let vs graunt Epiphanius more then this, that Timothie had the authoritie of the laying on of handes out of theſe woordes of the Apoſtle, Laye not handes ſodainely vpon any: Let vs graunt this too, that theſe duties belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged to the gouernors, yet we deny
<pb facs="tcp:21525:6"/> that Timothie could haue had any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie therefore, ouer the Elders of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, except he had bin an Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt. For Paule himſelfe Tim. 4. 14. doth ſhew ſufficiently that the laying on of the hands was done, in the name of the Elderſhip it ſelfe, not by the authoritie of any ſuperior. Now the reaſons of the ſame Epiphanius are theſe: Biſhops (ſaieth hee) begette the fathers of the Church, but Elders the ſonnes, in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as biſhops and not Elders ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned biſhops. But what is this els, then to aske to haue that which is in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for it may be and ought to bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that the biſhops tooke that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vpon them, without warrant of the word of God, and that the rule is falſe, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this matter, doth attribute it to the Apoſtles, which may be ſhewed by the ordaining of Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie by the Elderſhip. Againe, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as election is the chiefe ground of church-offices, which dependeth of the voyces of the whole company, and not of the laying on of handes, which made not biſhops, but ſent them into
<pb facs="tcp:21525:6"/> their poſſeſſion after they had made them: we may more truly affirme with the Apoſtle, that the holy Ghoſt by the voices of the children themſelues, made the fathers, and not the biſhops.</p>
               <p>An other of his reaſons is, a depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of places alleaged out of Paul, that the Church being new borne, biſhops could not be ſo eſtabliſhed euerywhere at the firſt, as is to be ſeene in the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Deacons. Whom yet can Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius perſwade, that it was for want of fit men onely, that there were many bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in euery Church? For that which not onelye Hierome, but Epiphanius againſt the Miletians alſo reporteth, concerning them of Alexandria: that is, Alexandria neuer had two biſhops, as the other cities, vpon what ground <note place="margin">Oupote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lexandr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> duo epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pous eich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> os kai al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poleis.</note> the men of Alexandria did it, &amp; folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the examples of other churches, let them ſee to it.</p>
               <p>Finally, that this kind of biſhop, which who ſo beareth it, is not the firſt in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der amongſt his felow elders, but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree aboue them, beyng the onely man in his dioceſſe, is not ordeined by the
<pb facs="tcp:21525:7"/> word of God, but by cuſtome amongſt the fathers Hierome witneſſeth, as very many others long ſince haue obſerued: For theſe are his woordes in his epiſtle to Euagrius.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle (ſaieth hee) doeth teach plainely, that Elders and Biſhops are all one, &amp;c. And where as one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was choſen to bee ſet ouer the reſt, that (ſaith he) was a remedy found out for remedy of ſchiſme, that euery one drawyng Chriſt vnto himſelfe, myght not rend the Church in ſunder. For at Alexandria alſo from the tyme of Marke the Euangeliſt, to the tyme of Heraclea and Dionyſius the Biſhop, the Elders placed one in a high degree or place, choſen by themſelues, whom they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a biſhop. Moreouer, vppon the firſt to Titus. An Elder and a Biſhop (ſaith hee) is all one, and before by the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the deuill, there was perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng in religion, it was ſayd amongeſt the people: I am of Paule, of Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, and of Caephas: the Churches were gouerned by the common aduiſe of the Elders. But after that euery one
<pb facs="tcp:21525:7"/> imagined, that thoſe whome he bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed were his owne, and not Chriſtes: it was decreed throughout the whole world, that one choſen of the Elders, ſhoulde bee ſet aboue the reſt; vnto whome all the care of the church might appertayne, to the takyng away of the ſeedes of contentions. And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, As the Elders knowe that they ate ſubiect by the cuſtome of the Churche to the Biſhop that is ſet ouer them: ſo let the Biſhops knowe, that they are greater then the Elders, rather by cuſtome, then by any vertue of the Lordes appoyntment. Yea and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine alſo in his 19. epiſtle ſaieth, that according to the titles of honor, which the vſe of the Church hath gotten, the office of a biſhop is greater then the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of an Elder.</p>
               <p>Chryſoſtome alſo witneſſeth, vpon the firſt to Timothie and the 3. chapter, That the Biſhops differ from the Elders onely in ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; that is (as Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact ſpeaketh more plainly) in the onely ceremonie of conſecration. Theodoret writing vpon the ſame place, ſaith, That
<pb facs="tcp:21525:8"/> in olde tyme they called the ſame men Elders and Biſhops, as though forſooth the thing it ſelfe had then bene onely called by another name, and goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to prooue that, becauſe Paule cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Epaphroditus the Apoſtle of the Philippians. This is of no weight at all. The names which are giuen of fellow labourer, and fellow ſouldiour, do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that he was no biſhop in this kind of biſhop, but an Euangeliſt tied to no one citie, much leſſe to a dioceſſe, of the number of thoſe, whome the Apoſtles did keepe, to ſend to and fro, at the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſpirit of God. The councell of Nice alſo, diſputing about the degrees of biſhops, alleageth ancient cuſtomes, whereof we minde to ſpeake anon. And where as Cyprian not in one place, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the biſhops ſucceſſors of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, whoſe authoritie is from God; and if we take it ſo, as though by the very commandement of God, theſe biſhops are the ſame, that in tyme paſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, the thing it ſelfe doth refute that, ſeeyng there was alwayes a certain por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſſigned to euery biſhop. But the
<pb facs="tcp:21525:8"/> Apoſtles, by the direction of the ſpirite rite of God, though not confuſedlie, did exerciſe their miniſtery throughout the whole worlde. But if this be true, there ſhould haue beene more biſhops, in the Church of Rome it ſelfe: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Peter and Paul, which yet afterwards was counted peculiar to one. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ther cannot be mo, the cheefe in one and the ſame company at one time. And whereas the name of Byſhops, is ſayd of the Apoſtleſhip. Acte. 1. 20. It maketh nothing to the matter, except a man by a like reaſon woulde haue the Deacons to haue bin Apoſtles, becauſe Paul calleth his Apoſtleſhip a Deacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or miniſtery. But we are to looke <note place="margin">Did<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nian</note> into that alſo, that Hierome mighte ſeeme to be of the mind, that this kinde of Byſhop begun the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when as ſchiſmes aroſe vp in the Church. That this is not ſo, we may gather out of Paul him ſelf, who of purpoſe writing to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians about the ſame matter, doth not onely paſſe ouer this remedy: but alſo as foreſeeing ſuch a matter, doth in the title of the epiſtle, ioyne vnto him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:21525:9"/> Soſthenes, to teach by his example how carefully this Primacie is to be auoyded in aſſemblies of the Church, who (it is euident were not onely the firſt in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der next vnto Chriſt, but alſo higheſt in degree) did execute their miniſterie in common. Wherefore, no not the ſame Paule alone would excommunicate the inceſtuous perſons by his Apoſtolicall authoritie, but by the authoritie of the whole Elderſhip, neither doeth Peter doubt to call himſelfe fellow elder. <note place="margin">Sunproſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteron.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Nay this is ſo farre off from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good remedy, from ſtaying of ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, that contrary wiſe there was neuer more bitter contention in the Church, then about this primacie which had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come to paſſe, if this preheminence aboue their fellowes had bene forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or rather, if men had neuer brought it in. Whereupon we conclude, that this kind of biſhop which is not of order, but of ſuperioritie, was brought in of man, &amp; as Hierome ſaith Tit. 1. by litle &amp; litle, &amp; that ſo as he is in deede thought, that the planets of diſſentions might be thereby plucked vp, all the care was
<pb facs="tcp:21525:9"/> committed to one man.</p>
               <p>And whereas he ſayth in the ſame place, that it was decreed thoroughout all the world: We are to vnderſtand it no otherwiſe, then of a priuy cuſtome, brought in by little &amp; little. And what ſoeuer is found in Ignatius, or other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, when the byſhop of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than was not yet found out, touching the authority of the byſhops or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers (as Iuſtin ſpeaketh) is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of this kind of Biſhop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE BISHOP OF THE <hi>Deuill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus alſo we deſcribe the biſhop of the deuill: that euen as that kind of biſhop ordained of God, degenerated by litle and litle, into an humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, whereof we intreated in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place: ſo this of the deuill, againſt which we now labour, is ſprouted forth of the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the biſhop brought in by man. Of this intollerable corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there are foule, moſt manifeſt, and vndoubted markes. Some of this kinde
<pb facs="tcp:21525:10"/> of biſhops haue wholy ſingled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the Elderſhips, ſo that they haue nothyng to do with them: Some haue wholy aboliſhed them. And that they haue chalenged vnto themſelues, and I knowe not to what Officials the whole guidance of the church, &amp; chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the authoritie to elect, to depoſe, and to excommunicate: ſo as they not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are aboue others, but as it were alone do exerciſe Lordſhip ouer Gods heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, contrary to the expreſſe inhibition of Peter.</p>
               <p>That alſo they haue inuaded vppon temporall dominions, contrary to the flat commaundement of Chriſt. And that they will not onely be preſent, but alſo Preſident in cauſes of this lyfe, and affaires of the Common wealth, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Apoſtle to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtandyng, 2. Tim. 2. 1. Cor. 6. yea and that of Chriſt himſelfe, Luke 13. 14.</p>
               <p>That alſo they waſte in riot &amp; ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe agaynſt conſcience and al ſhame, the goods conſecrate to holy vſes.</p>
               <p>That alſo they haue tied the ſpirit of
<pb facs="tcp:21525:10"/> God to certaine places and perſons, as though the biſhop of the more noble place, muſt needes haue neceſſary giftes aboue the reſt: or as though hee, who now is moſt fit, muſt needs be ſo alwais.</p>
               <p>And laſt of all, that they are the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of that beaſt which is deſcribed, Apoc. 13. as Pope Anacletus hymſelfe witneſſeth, epiſt. 2. in as much as they are diſtinguiſhed among themſelues, by thoſe their thrones and degrees, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the paterne of the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. The Apoſtle, Act. 20. 19. foretold of this Hierarchie, as they terme it, of the falſe biſhop, which in tyme became an Antichriſtian primacie. And in the 3. Iohn 9. it is moſt manifeſt, that Sathan begun euen then to lay the foundation of this myſterie.</p>
               <p>Now out of the hiſtory of the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Councell, which otherwiſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching doctrine was euery where recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it is cleare how foule diſſentions were euen then, of orderyng the bonds betweene the biſhops, the fountaines whereof they were ſo farre from dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng vg, that pretending auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,
<pb facs="tcp:21525:11"/> they confirmed the Patriarkſhip, and made a way for the horrible Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Rome then ſlidyng on, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlayd the ſeate for the harlot that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon ſeuen mountaines. But farre be it of, that theſe things, although they haue their auncient and great authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſhould be preiudiciall to the deuine and Apoſtolicall writings, according to the rule, whereof there is no wiſe man will doubt, that the Councels the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues are to be ſquared.</p>
               <p>And to what purpoſe ſhould I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute that agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betweene the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the Leuites, &amp; of Chriſt, which ſome old writers alleage to prooue this diueliſh oligarche, and at the length eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> playne tiranny. In deede it is euident, that the high prieſt was a figure of Chriſt himſelfe, whoſe ſecond image if we graunt that the biſhops are, it wil fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that there are as many images of Chriſt, as there be biſhops, in as much as there is none aboue him. But contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywiſe, no biſhop hath bene the image of Chriſt. Beſides, biſhops are not heds of the vniuerſall Church, but of their
<pb facs="tcp:21525:11"/> owne perticular: Nay, no heads at all, in as much as the Biſhops are vnder Archbiſhops, the Archb. vnder Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, and they agayne vnder the Pope, that is not vnder the true figure, but the counterfet figure of Chriſt. Now ſeeing that our onely hed is taken vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, a ſucceſſor for whom liuyng for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, we are not to ſeeke: who ſeeth not that the elders ordayned by the law of God, come in the roume of the prieſtes of the lawe, and the Deacons to anſwer to the Leuites?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>The firſt queſtion.</head>
               <p>Seeyng that there are ordayned in ſeuerall Churches, ſeuerall paſtors and miniſters, and the authority of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes miniſters in the Church ſeeme to be equall: Whether the office of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops be neceſſary in the church to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure meetings when occaſion ſerueth, admiſſion to the miniſterie, and remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng from the place vpon iuſt cauſes: or whether all the miniſters hauyng e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall authoritie, and not vnder the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb facs="tcp:21525:12"/> of any ſuperiour biſhop, ought to chuſe fit men with the conſent of the Patron who enioyeth the benefice, and the people the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, as alſo to correct &amp; remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the charge. And the maners of the people the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, who can hardly or not at all be kept in obedience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the bridle of the biſhops authority, which may runne through in viſityng of the Churches of the prouince, may put vs in mynd to retaine ſuch biſhops. Againe, ſo often as there ſhalbe dealing in matters touchyng the ſafetie of the common wealth in the ſolemne aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the land, accordyng to the laws which the kingdome hath of a long vſe and cuſtome receiued, there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eſtabliſhed without the biſhops, who haue the third roume and place in the kingdome, which to take away, or wholy to put downe, would bee very dangerous to the Common wealth.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The anſwer to the firſt queſtion.</head>
                  <p>Where as Sathans biſhop hath bene the ouerthrowe of the Church and all Chriſtian kingdomes, whoſe head is
<pb facs="tcp:21525:12"/> the Romaine Antichriſt, it is to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto of all handes, eſpecially of all godly princes, that they at once aboliſh it, if they minde the reformation of the Church, and their owne ſafetie. As for the biſhop ordained by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; brought into the Churche by little and little, whereby Sathan made him a waye for greater thinges, it had beene tolerable, ſo that with all the ancient good lawes prouidyng for the reſiſting of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernyng by ſome few, had bene in their former force agayne. But beſides, that the ſtate of the world being quite chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, experience of ſo many ages doeth teach vs too well, that vnleſſe this roote alſo be plucked vp, it wil come to paſſe, that the ſame fruite will ſprout and bud forth again. Finally, ſeing the Lord hath ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> decided this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie of ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority among his own diſciples, that he ſhut it cleane out, ſeing the rule both for doctrine &amp; good order of the Church, is to bee ſought for out of the very wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the apoſtles: &amp; it is manifeſted, the churches the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proſpered, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all this authoritie of one man ouer the reſt, yet
<pb facs="tcp:21525:13"/> was not, but as that grew vp, ſo al things fell to decay. Finally, ſeeyng where the remnants of this gouernment by a few, are not cleane taken away, the woorke of the Lord, is openly hindered: Our iudgement is, that after the chaſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of this deuiſe of man, the churches ſhall be wel prouided for, if they may be repaired according to the writynges of the Apoſtles. And the reformation as it ſemeth to vs, conſiſteth herein, that firſt the whole kingdome is to bee deuided into regions. Agayne, the regions into pariſhes, either of Cities or countrey townes: that in places moſt fit, and of greateſt aſſembly, be placed paſtors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng lawfully propounded by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of their owne elders, to the kinges chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maieſtie, or the deputies therof, and allowed of all. Laſtly, beyng recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of their own people, ouer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are to be ſet, they be placed, promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hauing gone before: and that in euery pariſh the paſtour may haue with hym fit men to aſſiſt him, who alſo may, beyng watchfull, ſalue vp the offences not ſo waighty, leauyng the other of
<pb facs="tcp:21525:13"/> greater importance, to the whole elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Alſo, that elderſhip made of the paſtors of pariſhes, both of citie &amp; cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and a ſufficient number of men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued for their godlines &amp; wiſedom, lawfully alſo choſen, as is aforeſayd, bee placed in moſt fitte places, who aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyng at a certaine tyme and place, may determine of the Church-affayres, of their owne gouernment, accordyng to the preſcript lawes, firſt ſet downe in a generall councell, and afterward confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the authoritie of the ſoueraigne maieſtie.</p>
                  <p>In this company let there be choſen by common voyces, one firſt in order not ſuperior in authoritie, who ſhall be thought moſt fit, and that without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king choyſe of any certaine place, &amp; but for a certaine tyme. After the expiryng whereof, either let another bee choſen, or els the ſame man is to be eſtabliſhed agayne for another tyme by a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: whoſe office is to make report of the common affaires to the company, to demaund their iudgements, and to giue ſentence by the iudgement of the
<pb facs="tcp:21525:14"/> elderſhip, hauing no authority giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ouer his felows, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather he is moſt ſubiect. In this aſſembly let nothyng be debated of beſides maters of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; that by the word of god, &amp; the lawes of church diſcipline eſtabliſhed, drawen out of the worde of God, not one whit medling with the authority of the ciuil magiſtrate. And let the ſoueraign maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty &amp; the lawfull magiſtrate thereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, be keepers of this order, &amp; the puniſher of thoſe that ſeditiouſly rage againſt it. But if any ſhal imagin that this ſodain aboliſhing of both theſe biſhops will miniſter occaſion of new ſtirres, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we ſee not with what conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the biſh. may ſo chalenge to themſelues the goods of the church, or els call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues biſhops, &amp; liue like princes of this world: yet for to keep the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peace, the ſoueraigne maieſty may leaue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which are now biſhops, their reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues whole for their lyfe tyme, ſo they trouble not the well made order of the Church, with prouiding there be none choſen into their place, when they bee dead. As for the frowardnes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:21525:14"/> it may be kept downe better a great deale by other reynes, then by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of a falſe named biſhop; as by preaching of the word of God, by cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the church, and the authoritie of the magiſtrate of the cuntry, agaynſt the open troubles of the publike ſtate, either eccleſiaſtical or ciuil. The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may very wel be viſited at ſet times without any great coſt and biſhoplike pride, by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery elderſhip hath choſen vnder the K. maieſties authority which wil not be alwais neceſſary, if the elders do rightly execute their office. This ſitting of the biſh. with the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the voice in the publike eſtates of the kingdom, came in with a manifeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the word, &amp; therfore in our mind is to be vtterly aboliſhed. For the biſh. hath nothing to do in ordring of meer ciuil affairs: yet foraſmuch as in ſuch aſſemblies, eſpecially ſome things many times happen, belonging to the eſtabliſhing of the eſtate, &amp; order of the churches: the kepers wherof the godly magiſtrates ought to be, &amp; not the ouer turners, as we are taught by the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple
<pb facs="tcp:21525:15"/> of holy kings. It is very neceſſary, that as often as the meetinges of the land are proclaymed, intelligence thereof be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the chiefe elders, who may bee preſent in the behalfe of their ſeigno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet not ſittyng as iudges, but dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling about matters of the church onely with the eſtates of the land, as their el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhips haue giuen them in charge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſtates thinke good vpon extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary occaſion, that they aske coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God about ſome other affaires alſo. If alſo the kinges Maieſtie thinke good to admit into counſell amongeſt the paſtors or elders, one, who ſhall bee thought to be wiſe and experienced in things, he may admit him, though not as a paſtor or elder, yet as a citizen. And it were iniurious to remooue from their office in the Church, the paſtours, and much leſſe the Elders and Deacons, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe laymen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that degree, which they hold as citizens, either in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, or in the aſſemblies. But the kings maieſty, and all the Princes &amp; Lordes, are to be exceedyng wary, that they make not courtlike gouernours of
<pb facs="tcp:21525:15"/> their paſtors, to the great endamagyng of the Church, as we haue a faire exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Euſebius of Nicomedia in the court of Conſtantine. As for the right of the patronage, leaſt ſome man ſhould ſay, that it was gotten for himſelfe. Our iudgement is, that it may be concealed, but not without ſome conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he which ſhall be choſen by the free voyces of the elderſhip, ſhould bee offred by the Patrone to the kings ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, beyng alſo to ſet vpon his charge, after the conſenting of his flocke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>The ſecond queſtion.</head>
               <p>After that religion is reformed, it hath bene a receiued cuſtome that the biſhops, and of the miniſters, paſtors &amp; elders, ſo many as ſhould be ſent of the biſhops, ſhould aſſemble themſelues, that they together with the chiefe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and nobles which profeſſe the true religion, might make enquirie after the doctrine and maners of euery one. But ſeeyng the prince himſelfe is a louer of the true religion, it is a queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:21525:16"/> there may be ſuch an aſſembly with out the conſent or commandement of the prince. Whether the miniſters alone may meete as often as they will. Laſt of all, whether the nobles and other godly men &amp; elders, (which are yeerely cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen with vs out of the people and nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie together) may lawfully or expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently come without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the king to ſuch aſſemblies. Which aſſembly of the nobles and people, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſome altogether needles vnder a godly prince, either becauſe it hath not long ſince ben receyued by a meere cuſtome without any law, and that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a prince, who then reſiſted the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whereby ſuch aſſemblies myght haue the greater authoritie: or els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may ſeeme dangerous, if ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nobles aſſemble ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without the conſent of the king, they may ſomtimes conſult of ſome thing els beſides reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>Others thinke that this aſſemblie is in no caſe to bee refuſed, but rather that it is very needefull that the Nobles and other religious men be preſent as
<pb facs="tcp:21525:16"/> helpers to their miniſters in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, bearyng witneſſe of their lyfe and the peoples behauiour, otherwyſe it will after come to paſſe, that if an impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prince raign afterward, that neither miniſters may ſafely aſſemble, neyther can the determination be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without the conſent, helpe &amp; ayde of the nobles.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>To the ſecond queſtion.</head>
                  <p>Councels are neceſſarye in the Church for many cauſes, both to the retayning of agreement, and alſo to the ſeeking of remedies by common aduiſe for the daungers which fall out. And laſt of all, to take order for thoſe that reſt not in the iudgement of perticular ſeignories, if they thinke they haue any iniurie done them. And theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels are eyther of a whole nation, or of ſome one Region or Prouince (or Dioceſſe as they haue begun to ſpeake after the deſcription of the Prouinces of Rome) deuided into many Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ories.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21525:17"/>
                  <p>It is neceſſary that the Councels of the prouinces be deuided for many cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; except there be other vrgent cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they would be appoynted rather e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery halfe yeere then quarterly, leaſt in diſcourſing of matters, they ſpende the tyme in vayne. And it will bee beſt for the auoyding of ambition, that the Councell be not alwayes aſſembled in the ſame place of euery prouince: but as ſoone as one halfe yeeres Synode is diſcuſſed, it may be determined by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent, where ſhal be the place of the next followyng. It will be very well that two of euery ſeignorie of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, choſen by common voyces, and ſent with ſome commiſſion, be preſent at theſe councels: one a paſtor, and the other an Elder or a Deacon. Neyther would we haue any ſtrife about ſitting, who ſhould ſitte firſt or laſt, but euery one to ſit, as it ſhall fall out without any contention, and the iudgement to bee giuen as any one ſhall ſit.</p>
                  <p>Now, he that ſhal gouern the whole action, who was choſen for this one thing by common conſent of voyce, the
<pb facs="tcp:21525:17"/> chiefe paſtor of the place, beyng in the beginning Preſident, which office ſhall end, when the Councell ſhall be ended. There are no matters in queſtion to bee propounded to theſe Councels to take knowledge of, but ſuch as are more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual &amp; belong to that prouince, where they are to be decided without appeale by the word of God, &amp; the rules there ſet downe, without any brabling or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of the company. Yet if any great priuate controuerſie ſhall fall out in the prouinciall Synode, where ſome may thinke that he hath cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne of iniury done vnto him, he may put vp his complaint to be decided in a generall councel, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhalbe thought good to aſſemble it.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore it is chiefly required, that if all the lawes of the Church be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed of the kings chriſtian maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: it foloweth, that the Councels are to be aſſembled by his commandement and direction, and not otherwiſe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet is there a new commiſſion eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tyme to be ſought for of the king for that purpoſe, ſeeyng his maieſty hath
<pb facs="tcp:21525:18"/> once eſtabliſhed a law touching the ſet tymes of ordinary Synodes. But yet if there ariſe iuſt cauſe of ſuſpition of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in theſe metings, other matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides meere eccleſiaſticall, it ſhall be ſafe for the kings maieſty to ſend one of his ſubiects who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he will, to diſgrace by his preſence the meeting of the Synodes: where yet he is not to be as a iudge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome thing fall out where it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the authoritie of the ciuill magiſtrate be put betweene.</p>
                  <p>A generall councel of the land is not to be aſſembled but vpon great cauſes, which ſeeyng they agree not with ſet tymes, it followeth, that they are not to bee ſtanding neither: but as often as ſome thing ſhall ſeeme to fall out of ſo great waight, either in doctrine or in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the church, as cannot well be decided but in a generall meeting, that prouince is to be carefull, to put o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouinces in mind concerning that matter, in theſe halfe yeeres Synodes: that with the conſent of all, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, they go vnto the kings maieſty, who (as being a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prince, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb facs="tcp:21525:18"/> nothing more, then the peace of the churches) ought without any ſtay or doubting, at the ſuite of the Churches, to appoint a place and tyme for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral meeting, as the need of the churches ſhal require. And the ſame order may ſeeme to be kept in the generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, which is in the prouincial, whether before the kings maieſty himſelfe, as in ſome general councels, the emperors of Rome haue bene preſent, or before the honorable lordes of the kings maieſtie. And laſt of all, whatſoeuer ſhal be alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the common conſent of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node, ſhall be confirmed by the kinges maieſties expreſſe authoritie, after the example of the godly Emperours.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>The third queſtion.</head>
               <p>Whether the king or the biſhops are to call the aſſembly of the Church, and as concernyng what matters they may make lawes.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>To the third queſtion.</head>
                  <p>Wee haue aunſwered the firſt part
<pb facs="tcp:21525:19"/> of this queſtion already. To the ſecond we anſwere. Firſt it is not lawful, no not for the angels themſelues, to make any lawes for the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but the church is to be vpholden by thoſe which the Lord hath enacted, ſeeyng we are now to looke for no newe reuelation, the whole counſell of God touchyng our ſaluation, being fully &amp; perfectly made manifeſt. Our iudgement alſo is, that the diſcipline or good order is to bee ſought for out of the word of God, and to be kept inuiolable, as the ſecond part of chriſtian doctrine. Yet there remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth two things, wherof there may, yea and there ought to be lawes ſet downe in the Church. For firſt of all, where as euery thyng is not expreſſely and in ſo many wordes ſet downe in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Prophetes and Apoſtles: therefore in controuerſies both concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning doctrine and the ſubſtaunce of Church diſcipline, the Councell ought to comprehend the decidyng of them in vnfallible and plaine heads, as by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne rules, like as it was done profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in thoſe right approoued Councels
<pb facs="tcp:21525:19"/> both Oecumenie &amp; perticulars, againſt the blaſphemy of the heretikes, and the malipertneſſe of the diſordered. And where as there come many queſtions in the ſeignories, eſpecially when there is dealing about mariages, though there cannot be certaine rules ſet downe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them out of the worde of God: yet ſo neere as may be, rules drawn out of the comparing of the ſcriptures, are to be ſet downe, after which they may be decided: yet is neither any thing take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the word of God, by the puttyng to of this, ſo it be rightly done. But this is rather an interpretation of the worde of God, &amp; a declaring how one folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon another. Agayne, where the ſubſtance both of doctrine and eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall diſcipline abideth whole and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable: yet muſt the outward cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the order needs be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for the ſame reaſon of the perſon &amp; places, abideth not alwayes. For we ſee the Apoſtles loue feaſtes taken away, &amp; the decrees touching bloud, and that which was ſtrangled. The gouernors of the church are to prouide alſo, that all
<pb facs="tcp:21525:20"/> may haue intelligence, at what tyme &amp; place it is expedient for any thing to be done in the Church: yet ſo as the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine it ſelfe, vnder which we alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the ordaining of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, abide whole as God hath ſet it downe. Further, that in ſetting down the lawes of this order, there be ſet down nothing fooliſh or vnprofitable, much leſſe any of the old cuſtomes retained, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is already ſtained with ſuperſtition, or which may eaſily make a way to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. Laſtly, that in all theſe, there be a great regard of ſimplicitie, and that the church be not loaded with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of rules.</p>
                  <p>And for the auoyding of the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of rites, it is neceſſary that theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, as in olde tyme they called them, be ſet downe in their generall counſels, that any thing in the ſame land may be chaunged according to the tyme. But whatſoeuer ſhall be ſet downe in thoſe counſels, is to be eſtabliſhed by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the kings Chriſtian maieſtie, as next after God, the keper and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the churches.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:21525:20"/>
               <head>The fourth queſtion.</head>
               <p>Whether the papiſtes are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate as Apoſtates, or vtter fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers away, or to be puniſhed with ſome ſmaller puniſhment.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>To the fourth queſtion.</head>
                  <p>We ſee not what ſword of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication may be drawen out againſt thoſe men, who though they were ſet into the church by no vaine baptiſme: yet neuer entred into the fellowſhip of the pure church. Yea the doores are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſtand ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they may come to heare the word of God, and they are carefully to be allured thether, if at any tyme (as the Apoſtle ſaith) they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and get out of the ſnare of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, of whom they are holden captiue. But if any ſhalbe thought to ſinne in an open contempt, our iudgement is, that it ought wholy to bee put ouer to the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſtrate. We thinke that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemeth a Chriſtian magiſtrate to deale much by lenitie in the matter of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards his ſubiects, not being trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſectaries, &amp; ſuch as of knowledge blaſpheme.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:21525:21"/>
               <head>The fift queſtion.</head>
               <p>For what cauſe may any be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated. As put caſe one kill a man, ſaying, he did it by chaunce, or of ſome neceſſitie for his owne ſafetie, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be iudged about that matter, not yet accuſed either of the king or of the neighbours of him that is killed: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may the Church make inquirie of the fact, whether it wer done of treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or by chance, or of neceſſity, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the manſlear to profeſſe repentance openly in the church, or to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate him if he refuſe.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>To the fift queſtion.</head>
                  <p>No man earneſtly repenting, is to be excommunicate, but after repentaunce, rather ought to bee receiued. And the cauſe of excommunication ought to be moſt waighty &amp; a publike offence, ſeing that onely the extremitie of the diſeaſes muſt haue extreme remedies. Yet may ſuch men after the thing be knowen, be ſuſpended from receiuyng the Lordes ſupper (they were woont to cal ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:21525:21"/> reſtrained) for whom this is thought to be a neceſſary remedy, that for the great nes of their offence, they may be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to others, or that their repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth ſtand in need of triall. As for the preſent queſtion. If the magiſtrate put in minde of his duety, doe winke at ſuch faults, and yet it be probable, that none is raſhly accuſed: Wee thinke that the Elderſhip may call him forth, and there as the matter ſhal require, to exhort him to the acknowledging of the offence: which if ye ſhall deny, he is to be left to the iudgement of God, neither are the Elders to proceede any further in the hearing of witneſſes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>The ſixt queſtion.</head>
               <p>Where as in the former age much wealth hath bene giuen by princes and many other, to the biſhops, monaſteries &amp;c. vnder the name of almes, &amp; ſo great riches ſeeme rather to hurt the biſhops, then to do them good: and monaſteries in the church and common wealth are vnprofitable: what yet ſhould become
<pb facs="tcp:21525:22"/> of ſuch goods which were once conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate to the church? For ſeeing the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and miniſters haue ſufficient of their tithes, whereof they may liue well and honeſtly, can the prince with the conſent of the ſtates of the kingdome, turne the reſidue eyther to his priuate vſe, or the good of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, eſpecially ſeeyng ſuch goods do conſiſt not onely in tithes, but of poſſeſſions, both in the country &amp; the city. Which queſtion, ſeeing it ſeemeth to bee rather ciuil then eccleſiaſticall, I purpoſed not to trouble you in this point. But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as many both learned &amp; godly amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, are of this minde, that thoſe thinges which haue bene once vowed to holy vſes, cannot be giuen to prophane vſes, though they be publike, I could not but mention the matter vnto you.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>To the ſixt question.</head>
                  <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the goods of the church. Firſt of all we ſuppoſe great heed ought to be taken, that none do ſtaine himſelf with handling the church goods. For if God hath taken reuenge of ſuch ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges,
<pb facs="tcp:21525:22"/> euen amongſt the very idolaters: what trow we will his iudgement be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue ſpoiled his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and haue prophaned the thinges which were ſet a parte for his true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer it is euident, that this tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth greatly to the reproch of the name of God and of his holy goſpel, as thogh forſooth papiſtry hath ben abandoned, not for the loue of the truth, but to rob the church of her goods, and as though new theeues haue entered in the roume of the olde. Nowe, euen as aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce doth ouerwhelme the Church, ſo it is to be feared, leaſt ſhe be brought into great ſtraights by want, whileſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny now a daies are no leſſe ſparyng and niggardly in vpholding the true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, then heretofore kinges and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces themſelues haue beene ouerlaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng: we thinke it needefull to keepe a meane in this poynte, which ſo wee take will be the beſt, if firſt a view be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the daily expences which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be made: then if ſomwhat be laid vp for many thinges extraordinary,
<pb facs="tcp:21525:23"/> wheras no iuſt reckoning can be made, and both of theſe be accounted not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly or ſlenderly, but bountifully and liberally, ſeeyng that the Church by the goodnes of God hath plenty. Therfore that number is to bee made of pariſhes and paſtors which may very well ſuffiſe the people, and euery one is to haue an honeſt liuing allowed. Order alſo is to be taken for the elders, who are to aſſiſt the paſtors that they may conueniently diſcharge their duety. It would be alſo iniurious, that the widowes and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the paſtors which are dead, ſhould be brought to beggery, who in a care of their calling, were conſtrained to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the care of prouiding for their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie. Schooles alſo and vniuerſities, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are the Seminary of the church are not the leaſt part of the care thereof. Care alſo is to bee had of almes houſes &amp; hoſpitals, &amp; of churches, that they be kept in reparations, and new builded if need require. Laſt of all (as I ſay before) ſeeyng the churches haue plenty, order muſt be taken, what ſhal be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church treaſury yeerely, from
<pb facs="tcp:21525:23"/> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce may be fetched that which may ſuffiſe in tyme of warre or famine, leaſt then it be to ſeeke when it ſhould be in a readineſſe. When all theſe things ſhall faithfully &amp; frankly be brought by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation into one ſumme ſtill yeerely: Good and ſufficient men are to take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for their collecting, ſuch a way as ſhall be without trouble or ſtrife. That which ſhall be found to be ouerplus, is not to be lauiſhed out with other pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like reuenues, but to be layed vp by it ſelfe (for theſe are of an other nature, though not alwayes gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſteſt ſort by the couetous prieſts) and we thinke that it may be taken &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed for the ſeruice of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, when the publike neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof doth require it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if the people be ſo much the more eaſed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
